Good טוב *tov*. Today's דף *daf* is ל"ח *lamed chet* and quiet
everybody, we really are going to make a push because this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, the remainder of yesterday's דף *daf*, we're behind on ל"ז
עמוד ב' *lamed zayin amud bet* and today's דף *daf* I think
should go quickly, so we're really going to make a push, so
let's focus and we're going to catch up today. Okay, so we're
on ל"ז עמוד ב' *lamed zayin amud bet* and we have referred
to the debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי
טרפון Rebbi Tarfon, *Rabbi Tarfon* about somebody who steals who says to
five people, "I stole from one of you, I don't know which
one." רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon* says, "Well, you just deposit
the money and you walk away," which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
a little aghast at so it modifies it to say it means
you put the money in escrow and you walk away. And רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says you have to pay full. So
now we've looked at רבי טרפון Rebbi Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon*, we're now
going to look a little more closely at רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva's
*Rabbi Akiva*. So, אמר רב ספרא *Amar Rav Safra*, it's about eight
lines down beginning of the line. אמר רב ספרא *Amar Rav Safra*,
I'm sorry, ויניח *Veyaniach*? No, I'm sorry. אמר ליה Amar Lei, אביי
לרבא *Amar lei Abaye le-Rava*, so Abaye said to Rava, "מי אמר
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva לא זו הדרך מוציאה מידי midi עבירה *Mi
amar Rabbi Akiva lo zu haderech motzia mi-yedei aveira*? Did Rabbi Akiva
really say this isn't the way to get out of transgression, to
only to put the money in escrow? עד שישלם לכל אחד ואחד
*Ad sheyeshalem lekhol echad ve'echad*, you have to pay everybody up. אלמא
מספיקא מפקינן ממונא *Alma misfeika mafkinan mamona*, you see that Rabbi Akiva
says that you do pay money out even if there's a doubt,
that you don't go by the principle of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
*hamotzi mechavero
alav
hara'aya*." Now, of course the obvious question is, does he mean that
as a matter of law, or does he mean that as בא
לצאת ידי שמים Ba Latzeit Yedei Shamayim, *ba latzet yedei shamayim*? רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva? *Rabbi Akiva* does say, "This is not the way
to be free of sin," sounds like he's talking about some moral
religious obligation, not about a technical legal obligation. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is bracketing that. It's going to circle back to it. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is bracketing it. Okay, and it says, "Oh
okay, so he doesn't hold to this whole principle of חזקה Chazakah
*chazaka*, that even out of a doubt you would have to pay
out money." Now, it's a little absurd to think that he doesn't
hold to the principle of חזקה Chazakah *chazaka*, that's what the system
is based on. If you claim I owe you money, you have
the burden of proof. But as תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* points out, you
know, and there's a whole other question about the question about like
maybe the point here is another debate, which is fascinating, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* doesn't bring up, which is the debate about ברי ושמא
Bari Veshema *bari ve-shema*. You know, you come and you say, "Dov,
you stole from me a hundred dollars," and everybody here around the
table says that, and I say, "I don't know." So you're all
a ברי Bari *bari*, I'm a שמא Shema *shema*. Maybe that's the
point, that a definite claim against a doubt wins out even though
I have the money. So that's possible. That is a position in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. It's interesting the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't reference
that. So the other point to make here is the point that
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* makes, which is, in this case I definitely admit
that I owe somebody money. The question is which one? So it's
not like your standard חזקה Chazakah *chazaka*. Your standard חזקה Chazakah. *chazaka*
even if I say שמא Shema, *shema* is, you say to me
everybody here says I owe you a hundred dollars and I say,
"I don't know, maybe I don't owe anybody, maybe I owe all
of you." Okay, so that case maybe I don't pay out money
because you have the burden of proof. But when I admit that
I owe money and I just don't know to whom, maybe the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, "Oh okay, so according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* it looks like even though you've got a doubt
and even though you're מוחזק Muchzak *muchzak*, you gotta pay everybody out."
Is that really true? ורמינהי *Ur-min-hi*, I'll ask you on this. I'm
sorry. נפל הבית עליו ועל אמו *Nafal habayit alav ve-al immo*. So
let's say a building collapses on a child and his mother—not a
child, a man and his mother. Okay. And the question is who
died first? Because
if
the mother dies first, then her son, the other guy in the
building, inherits her. And then if the son dies, all of the
son's heirs inherit from him. So the son's heirs would like the
order to have been the mother died first and then the son.
If it was the reverse, the son died first, okay, then his
heirs inherit his smaller estate. And then the mother died. So if
her mother dies now without sons, who inherits the mother? Well, it
would be her father, her brothers, okay, it would be other people.
So the son's heirs would be out of the picture. Okay, so
the son's heirs want the mother to have died first and the
mother's heirs want the son to have died first. Okay, and you
don't know which happened. נפל הבית עליו ועל אמו *Nafal habayit alav
ve-al immo*. יורשי הבן אומרים האם מתה ראשונה *Yorshei habben omrim ha-em
meta rishona*. יורשי האם אומרים הבן מת ראשון *Yorshei ha-em omrim habben
met rishon*. Okay, so each one claims it was the order that
privileges them—or whatever, that benefits them. אלו ואלו מודים שיחלוקו *Elu ve-elu
modim sheyachloku*. There was a debate of בית הלל *Beit Hillel* and
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* about other similar cases. In this case everybody
agrees there's no way to determine it, everyone and the money is
obviously goes out of the mother's estate, the question is who gets
it, you have no idea everybody has an equal possibility, you split
it. ואמר רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Ve-amar Rabbi Akiva*, but Rabbi Akiva
says, "No, מודה אני בזו *Modeh ani bezu*, in this one I
agree—I agree to who is a different question. But anyway, in this
one I say שהנכסים בחזקתם *she-hanechasim be-chezkatan*, they remain in their חזקה
Chazakah, *chazaka*." So what does it mean they remain in their חזקה
Chazakah, *chazaka*? That almost begs the question: who's considered מוחזק Muchzak *muchzak*,
the mother's heirs or the son's heirs? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* tries to figure that out. But for us, that we don't
care about that. Because if it doesn't really matter who's מוחזק *muchzak*,
he basically says that מוחזק *muchzak* wins and you don't say everybody's
got an equal claim. the money is has to go out, just
like when I admit I owe somebody a hundred dollars, I just
don't know who. The money has to go out, right? And there,
in one case, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says you pay everybody. Now
here of course you can't pay everybody, but anyway, so presumably the
alternative is you split it. But no, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva. says
מוחזק trumps.
Right. So why does he say מוחזק trumps here and not in
the case of גזילה? Gezeilah?
Because there's another alternative that no one's saying, in other words, splitting
it means that someone may come out ahead or behind because if
there is one... I understand. So take a proportion of it.
All right, that's fine, that's different. There's really only one set of
heirs. Actually, I'm sorry, I do an typo of ביכול, Biyachol, that's
fine. Let's see the גמרא Gemara says, the point is that he
says the money goes stays in the חזקה Chazakah and in our
case he doesn't. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה, התם, Hatam, שמא ושמא. Shema Veshema. Okay, in that case,
nobody knows the order that the people died. So everybody has a
doubtful claim. So then the money gets sort of split up equally.
גזל אחד מחמשה, Gezel Echad Michamisha, ברי ושמא Bari Veshema. הוא. Hu.
In this and it goes out of the, I'm sorry, I said
that wrong. Everybody has a doubtful claim so חזקה Chazakah trumps. חזקה
chazakah wins. In this case, it's a ברי ושמא. Bari Veshema I,
you say I owe you, I stole from you, you say I
stole from you, you say I stole from you, whatever, and I
say I don't know. So in that case, and now the גמרא
Gemara? does introduce the ברי ושמא Bari Veshema language, maybe in that
case is when רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva. says you pay everybody with
a definite claim.
Well, there's are also...
Well, that's the obvious counterpoint.
On the one hand, the more reason to pay here than a
normal ברי ושמא Bari Veshema is that I also admit I owe
money to someone. On the other hand, more reason to not pay
here than a normal ברי ושמא Bari Veshema, is every ברי Bari
contradicts one another and I certainly don't owe everybody. Okay, but anyway
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is maybe רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva
position is ברי Bari, wins, okay, maybe plus some of those other
factors, but when there's nobody's a ברי, Bari? then it's you go
by חזקה.
chazakah גזל אחד מחמשה, Gezel Echad Michamisha, ברי ושמא, Bari Veshema, what's
the ברי?
Bari
Everybody says, all of you guys are saying I definitely stole from
you. Right.
Okay.
No, that's an answer. That's how רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva doesn't contradict
himself. וחזקה Vechazakah wins when it's all a שמא Shema, and you
pay out the money when the other people are making ברי claims.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והא מתניתין דהכא, Veha Matnitin Dehacha, אמר
לשנים גזלתי לאחד מכם Amar Lishnayim Gezalti Leachad Mikem מנה, Maneh, but
one minute, in our משנה Mishnah where the guy comes forward and
he says I stole from one of you and they're not making
claims against the guy, דשמא ושמא הוא, Deshema Veshema Hu, everybody's making
a doubtful claim, וקתני, Ukatani, הוא נותן לזה מנה ולזה מנה, Hu
Noten Laze Maneh Ulaze Maneh, and it says you pay everybody out,
so you see, even by a שמא ושמא, Shema Veshema, you don't
go by חזקה, you pay everybody out. So the גמרא Gemara says,
wait a minute, וממאי דרבי עקיבא היא, Umimai Derebbi Akiva Hi, what
makes you think that that משנה Mishnah is רבי עקיבא? Rebbi Akiva
Now, of course, the point is, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva argued and
רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva right about I
stole from five people, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the one
who was always more willing to pay out the money. So it
almost makes obvious sense that that has to be רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva דקתני עלה דההיא, Dekatani Alah Dehahi, so the גמרא Gemara says,
because we taught, מודה רבי טרפון Modeh Rebbi Tarfon באומר לשנים גזלתי
לאחד מכם Beomer Lishnayim Gezalti Leachad Mikem מנה Maneh ואיני יודע איזה
מכם, Veini Yodea Eizeh Mikem, even though רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon generally
says you can put the money in escrow and walk away, when
you come forward and you say I don't know which one, which
one I stole from, there he agrees that you pay everybody out.
He basically, it is the author of our משנה Mishnah and agrees
that when you come forward, you pay everybody out. So who is
he agreeing to? Well, who's the normal person who says you pay
everybody out? רבי עקיבא. למאן מודה, Leman Modeh, who's he agreeing to?
לרבי עקיבא בר פלוגתיה. Lerebbi Akiva Bar Plugteih. So look, רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon normally says you don't pay everybody out. But in our
משנה Mishnah when the guy comes forward, he agrees to רבי עקיבא
and says you pay everybody out. So obviously רבי עקיבא in our
משנה Mishnah says you pay everybody out. So in a way we've
come full circle, why in the גזילה Gezeilah case, why, excuse me,
why in the case of the house that collapsed that everybody is
a שמא, you say it retains the חזקה, but in the case
of the משנה Mishnah where the guy comes forward and everybody's a
שמא, you pay everybody out. Now we already answered that. The obvious
answer is בא לצאת ידי שמים, latzeit yedei shamayim, right? So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara. says, no. אוקימנא לה בבא
לצאת ידי שמים, Okimna Lah Beva Latzeit Yedei Shamayim, as Michael says
why are we doing this whole גמרא. Gemara Okay, we've already given
the answer, maybe we're reinforcing that that's פשט Pshat of the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so in the case where somebody says, וממאי דשמא ושמא
הוא, Umimai Deshema Veshema Hu, now what makes you think that our
משנה Mishnah is שמא ושמא? Shema Veshema? Maybe again it's a ברי
ושמא, maybe that's a related
factor, חדא דלא קתני תובעין אותו, Chada Delo Katani Tovin Oto,
first of all because the משנה Mishnah never said the other side
was demanding the money, it had them silent, so presumably they were
clueless. ועוד התני רבי חייא, Veod Hatani Rebbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rebbi
Chiya actually clarifies in a ברייתא Braita that that's the case of
the משנה. Mishnah. זה אינו יודע וזה אינו יודע. Ze Eino Yodea
Veze Eino Yodea. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's the answer?
Right? And in another way of asking this, why does רבי עקיבא
in one case say pay all the people out that say I
owe them money? I don't know, he actually says that in both
cases. But anyway, how's it different than the collapsing house? Why in
the collapsing house do you keep the... do you have חזקה wins,
whereas in these cases you pay everybody out? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, אוקימנא לה בבא לצאת ידי שמים, Okimna Lah Beva Latzeit
Yedei Shamayim, as Michael says why are we doing this whole גמרא?
Gemara. Okay, we've already given the answer, maybe we're reinforcing that that's
פשט Pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so in the case where
somebody says... I stole from one of you and I don't know
which one, okay, there רבי עקיבא and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon debate,
do you just put the money down and walk away or do
you put in escrow and walk away or do you pay everybody
out? Okay, but if in our משנה, mishna, right, in that case
when you're sort of coming forward on your own, okay, because that
was, you know, it's ironic. In that case where they're demanding and
everybody is saying I stole from them, okay, and they're making a
claim against me, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon, says just put it in
escrow because what I'm, I'm not trying to be לצאת ידי שמים,
I'm just trying to do my legal obligation. Okay, so that's where
רבי עקיבא and רבי טרפון can debate. But if I come forward,
then if even if nobody is making a claim against me and
I say I don't know which of from the five of you
I stole from, then רבי עקיבא and רבי טרפון both agree that
you pay everybody out. Okay, and that's our משנה. mishna. Okay, let's
wrap this up. And the גמרא Gemara says like this: ומי אמר
רבא כל בשתי כריכות הוי ליה למידק. u'mi amar Rava kol b'shtei
krichot havei lei l'midak. Now we're going back to a point we
made yesterday, which is that in the case where two people
give me money to guard for them, one of you gave me
200, one gave me 100, and I can't remember which one, right?
So the question is do I have to put the extra 100
in escrow, pay you each 100 and put the third 100 in
escrow, or is it my fault, my negligence, and I pay you
each 200? So רבא Rava distinguished between a case where I could
say, hey you guys weren't careful about seeing what each other was
depositing and knowing that you could make a claim against, you know,
you were, Michael, you came together with Eli, you know, so if
you weren't looking at one another, you clearly weren't scared that one
of you would make a false claim based on what the other
person deposited. So therefore I didn't have to be so careful and
I wasn't negligent. But in a case where you came on different
days and I can't remember who gave me what, then רבא Rava
says well then I am negligent and I have to pay each
one of you out. So that's the difference, שתי כריכות, shtei krichot,
two separate bundles is like basically essentially two separate days and then
I'm negligent and I pay everybody out as opposed to when I'm
not negligent and you came at the same time and then I
put the doubtful money in escrow. All right, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ומי אמר רבא כל בשתי כריכות הוי ליה למידק.
u'mi amar Rava kol b'shtei krichot havei lei l'midak. Does רבא Rava
really say when they come in two separate times you need to
be careful and if you can't remember you're
negligent? ואמר רבא ואיתימא רב פפא הכל מודים בשנים שהפקידו אצל רועה
שמניח רועה ביניהם ומסתלק. v'amar Rava v'itayma Rav Pappa hakol modim b'shnayim
she'hikidhu eitzel ro'eh she'mani'ach ro'eh beineihem u'mistaleik. This debate of רבי עקיבא
and רבי טרפון, I can't remember who I stole from, everybody would
agree that if two people deposited money by a shepherd, then the
person could just and it wasn't a case of stealing and whatever
and presumably no negligence on the part of the shepherd, the shepherd
doesn't remember who gave him, who gave him two sheep and who
gave him one sheep. In that case he just puts the
questioned sheep in escrow and he walks away. Okay, so the question
is that
why don't we assume that that's a case
of, so
that should be a case of
שתי כריכות. shtei krichot. Right, that should normally be a case of
me assuming that I should have been careful to pay attention. And
therefore why am I not the shepherd who doesn't know, why don't
I have to give everybody two sheep? Why shouldn't I have been
paying attention? Now the question is how do we know I should
have been paying attention in that case? Maybe the two of you
came at the same time, the same way when you gave me
200 and 100 you came at the same time. How do we
know there I should be paying more attention? Okay, so רש"י, Rashi,
a little bit of a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. I'll
just tell you רש"י's Rashi explanation. רש"י's Rashi explanation is because it's
very visible, right? I have no basis like oh you each gave
me a bundle, I didn't at the moment open up the bundle
and count out the money, and you were anyway coming at the
same time, I wasn't paying so much attention, whatever. Here it is
so visible that obviously I was negligent not to be paying attention
to who was giving me what. So in that case if that's
true why according to רבא Rava shouldn't the shepherd have to pay
each person out in full? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה
התם כשפקידו בעדרו של רועה שלא מדעתו. amar lei hasham k'she'hikidhu b'edro
shel ro'eh she'lo mida'ato. No, the point there is they didn't both
present it to the shepherd. I know Michael came and said to
me, Dov, I left my sheep off in your, you know, in
the flock, I'll come pick it up at the end of the
day. Okay, and Eli says the same thing to me. Exactly, and
Eli says the same thing to me. So I didn't even see.
Now you could say I should have asked you how many. But
anyway, meaning שלא מדעתו she'lo mida'ato it really means without my seeing.
Right, you deposited it and you told me I dropped them off
on your, whatever, and you didn't tell me how many. Okay, anyway,
moving on. וכן שני כלים אחד יפה מנה ואחד אלף זוז. v'chein
shnei keilim echad yafeh maneh v'echad alfuz uz. And if there also
is two vessels, one is worth 200 and one 1000 and one
worth 100 and everybody is debating which the more expensive one is
theirs, it says you give one guy the 100 one, you break
the second one, literally. Now I would have said it's figurative and
it means that you sell it and you give the 100 dollars
to the second party and you put the rest of the money
in escrow. But the גמרא Gemara is going to read this idea
of break the second one. literally, and I don't really understand that.
Let's go look at the גמרא. Gemara וצריכא, U'tzricha, you need both
the case of vessels and the case of money, two hundred and
one hundred debating who get put what. דאישמעינן הך קמייתא, De'ishmiyenu hach
kamaisa, if it just said the case of money, בהא קאמרי רבנן,
behach ka'amri Rabanan, that's where the Rabbis say that you put the
money in escrow, because doing this type of a thing doesn't cause
any loss, משום דליכא פסידא, mishum de'leika pseida, but here that the
larger vessel is being damaged, okay, אבל בהא דאיכא פסידא דגודא, aval
behach de'ika pseida d'guda, אימא מודי ליה לרבי יוסי, eima modei lei
le'Rabbi Yosi, then they might agree to Rabbi Yosi, which is like
it's really a
Solomonic solution, right? So you break the vessel in half. So maybe
they say to Rabbi Yosi, since it's going to happen anyway, the
idea of pay out and put the rest in escrow is not
an efficient solution here. Let's just put it all in escrow. ואי
איתמר בהא, Ve'i itmar behach, if we just said that in the
case of the vessel, בהא קאמר רבי יוסי, behach ka'amar Rabbi Yosi,
that's maybe where Rabbi Yosi says put it all in escrow so
you don't have to break the
vessel. אבל בהא אימא מודי להו לרבנן, Aval behach eima modei lehu
le'Rabanan, but if it's just money, maybe he agrees that the Rabbis'
solution is an easier one. וצריכא, U'tzricha, you need both reasons. Now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, you can't say that Rabbi Yosi
would be more inclined to say his position in the case of
where you would have to break the thing and it would cause
a loss. Because that's not the logic of
Rabbi Yosi's position. The גמרא Gemara says וטעמיה דרבי יוסי משום הפסד
הרמאי הוא. V'tamei d'Rabbi Yosi mishum hefsed ha'ramai hu. Wait a minute,
Rabbi Yosi's reason of putting it all in escrow was to create
a disincentive for somebody to lie. So it's not a bigger, there's
no more compelling reason, oh, let's put it all in escrow because
if I were to break it up it would cause a loss
to the vessel. That's completely irrelevant to my position. That's a nice
fact, but my position is you have to create disincentive so people
lie. So of course I'm going to always say put the money
in escrow. I don't care if we're dealing with money, you're dealing
with vessels, right? I'm not going to let the guy walk away
with his money. I'm going to put it all in escrow. Right,
remember that whole point there? If you can say two hundred and
you're still going to get your hundred, there's nothing stopping you. So
the logic of Rabbi Yosi's position is not different just because the
vessel is going to be lost. So you can't say you need
the second case because maybe Rabbi Yosi is limited to the second
case. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא תרווייהו לרבנן. Ela traveihu le'Rabanan.
Fine. Rabbi Yosi obviously would say his position in both cases. But
the חידוש chiddush is for the Rabbis. איצטריכא. Itzricha. לא זו אף
זו קתני. Lo zu af zu katani. Not only do the Rabbis
say in the case of the cash that you give each person
a hundred and you put the third hundred in escrow, even in
the case of the vessel where it requires this solution, requires breaking
the vessel and causing a loss, you know,
to the rightful owner, I mean, and it's really not fair. I'm
telling the truth, it's my thousand dollar thing, because he's lying, you're
now going to break my gorgeous מנורה menorah and break it in
half and give me a little piece of it? Right, it is
a crazy solution, right? And so that's the חידוש, chiddush, that even
in that case, the Rabbis say that's what you do and you
put the rest in escrow. Again, I don't know, but I do
want to say that I cannot begin to understand why I would
physically break the vessel rather than sell it. Okay, and anyway, so
let's go on. Let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
But what if it was an unbreakable vessel let's say?
Yeah, then you would have to. Okay, let's look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. Impossible. Okay, we are moving on. All right. No questions.
No, no, no. All questions later. We're catching up. המפקיד פירות אצל
חבירו, Hamaphkid peirot etzel chaveiro, another special case about a פיקדון. pikadon.
Okay, you entrust fruit to a friend, which often means grain, but
whatever it is. אפילו הן אבודין לא יגע בהן. Afilu hein avudin
lo yiga bahen. Even if they are wasting away, don't touch them.
Now you might remember a discussion by finding a lost object that
under certain cases where maintaining it costs me too much money and
you're going to have to reimburse me, so in order to protect
your property, I am actually entitled and empowered to go sell it
and put the money away and hold on to the money for
you. Here though, it's different. Here you knowingly gave me the object
to watch and you did not give me any specific instructions, okay?
So even if right now, you know, the object is rotting and
it's moldy and
whatever, you know, since you didn't give me any specific
instructions, I am not empowered to sell it. Now which is funny,
because you would actually think that part of my obligation to watch
it is to protect its value, okay? So, and there might be
some discretionary cases where you would say since you don't have specific
instructions, don't do anything, but certain cases would seem like obviously you
have to act. And we'll see that, that's the next line in
the
משנה. Mishnah. רבן גמליאל אומר מוכרן בפני בית דין, Rabban Gamliel omer
mochran bifnei Beit Din, you do it in the presence of the
court, so there's no question, like nobody thinks you're cheating anybody, okay?
So you get some external sort of validation to that. מפני שהוא
כמשיב אבידה לבעלים. mipnei she'hu k'meishiv aveidah l'ba'alim.
And there's that אבידה aveidah discussion, right? So you are actually, its
value is being lost and you're protecting them from a loss and
that's your mandate. All right, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reasoning of the תנא
קמא? Tanna Kamma? רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel makes a lot of
sense. אמר רב כהנא אדם רוצה בקב שלו מתשעה קבין של חבירו.
Amar Rav Kahana adam rotzeh b'kav shelo mi'tishah kabin shel chaveiro. That's
a great line, okay? A person would rather have one box of
his own grain rather than nine boxes of somebody else's. Now this
obviously, you know, I mean, it's I guess it's true. Well, it's
also, it's harder for us to relate... well, we'll see where this
leads but it's harder for us to relate to. because you know
we're not like farmers or whatever and you know what do I
care you know if it's this box of tomatoes or that but
imagine that you had a little a little tomato patch in your
backyard and these are your homegrown tomatoes and I'm coming over and
I'm saying to you you know Micah I have nine boxes of
gorgeous tomatoes from Holland trust me they taste so much better than
yours will you swap me for them and you're like get the
heck out of here I just worked the whole season growing these
tomatoes right so to some degree that makes sense on the other
hand probably we're also dealing with people that are more farmers for
a business and not people with little tomato patches in their backyard
okay but nevertheless that's the argument I would rather have my stuff
rather than to save the value presumably there's still a sense that
some of it can be salvaged right and obviously if it's all
going to waste the argument loses its force okay that's one explanation
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אמר *Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar* no חשינן שמא התנה המפקיד תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros. מקום
אחר *chashinan shema tana hamafkit trumos u'maasros makom acher* the reason I
can't sell them is of course my responsibility to the owner who
tell me to sell them but since the owner knows that I've
been watching them he might in his home say oh I've got
to take תרומות trumos *Trumos* and מעשרות maissros *Maasros* you know what
my תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros* will be that stuff that Dov
is watching for me now I'm going to sell that stuff because
I have no idea you did that I'm going to sell that
stuff to somebody and that unwitting person I'm unwitting the other person's
unwitting and they're going to eat תרומה terumah, *Truma* okay so that's
why I can't do it because I don't know how the owners
have treated that object דאמר
במקום אחר *d'amar b'makom acher* set
meaning that based on grain that the owner has back in his
home that's a different place this is תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros*
on what's the grain back in the owner's home okay that's why
it's not because of my responsibility to the owner it's because of
my responsibility to the person I'm selling it to okay מתיבי *mesivei*
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* how's
תרומה terumah *Truma* if it sits in your
yes so that's a good question which תוספות *Tosfos* asks which is
you it is possible to take תרומה terumah, *Truma* even if they're
not all physically in the same space as long as it's under
your control so I could say that grain that I have in
France that's being watched for me by my friend Frederique over there
that is תרומה terumah *Truma* on the grain that I have here
in in America the only problem תוספות *Tosfos* says is לכתחילה *l'chat-chila*
you're not supposed to do it okay so תוספות *Tosfos* deals with
like under what circumstances might you be allowed to do it but
it does work
but but if I know it's sitting there and rotting doesn't that
no but the owner doesn't know it's rotting that's the point the
owner is off somewhere in France he had me watch this he's
gone on his vacation or checking out his fields in France and
he has no idea and I can't reach him before the age
of telephones right so he thinks it's secure with me and is
taking תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros* and I see that it's rotting
and I'm going to go sell it and then you know so
the people are going to be hurt in the process
shouldn't he check to
see that to begin with okay so well but you didn't guess
what people don't always think in advance מתיבי *mesivei* I'll ask you
on this המפקיד פירות אצל חברו הרי זה לא יגע בהן Haray
zeh lo yiga bahen. *hamafkid peiros etzel chaveiro harei zeh lo yiga
bahen* we have a ברייתא *Baraisa* that says that if you entrust
it you should not touch it הרי זה לא יגע בהן *harei
zeh lo yiga bahen* לפיכך *l'fichach* because you know that the watcher
is a the gard- the שומר shomer *Shomer* is not allowed to
touch it בעל הבית עושה אותן תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros, במקום אחר
*baal habayis oseh otan Trumos u'Maasros b'makom acher* the owner can be
confident that they're still there and therefore he's allowed to use it
to take תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros* from grain somewhere else so
that sounds like taking תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros* is an effect
of the law of not selling it it's not the cause of
the law of not selling it so בשלמא *bishlama* for רב כהנא
Rav Kahana? *Rav Kahana* for רב כהנא Rav Kahana *Rav Kahana* says
the reason you don't sell it is because people want their own
property היינו דקתני לפיכך *hayinu d'katani l'fichach* that's why it's a you
know it's a it's an effect of this rule אלא *ella* רב
נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* מאי
לפיכך *mai l'fichach* for רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
*Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* this is the reason not to sell it
so what do you mean oh because you can't sell it therefore
you can you know it can't be therefore the owner can be
מפריש mafrish, *mafrish* that's the reason you can't sell it so גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says no הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar* here's how to read
it השתא דאמרי רבנן לא נזבן דחשינן *hashata d'amri Rabbanan lo nizban
d'chashinan* now that the רבנן *Rabbanan* tell the שומר Shomer *Shomer* don't
sell it because maybe the owner will take תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות
*Maasros* so therefore now that that's the הלכה halacha. *halacha* now the
owner can be confident that they're not sold and therefore he can
take תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros* לפיכך בעל הבית עושה אותן תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros במקום אחר *l'fichach baal habayis oseh otan Trumos u'Maasros
b'makom acher* so before we had that rule it still might have
happened that the owner would have taken תרומות *Trumos* and מעשרות *Maasros*
right but but if you were to ask בית דין beit din
*Beis Din* you were to ask a Rabbi hey can I assume
that my stuff is still there and take it I would say
no no you can't assume it maybe he's maybe he's selling it
but now that the רבנן *Rabbanan* say oh but not everybody asks
the Rabbi and sometimes people will be מפריש mafrish *mafrish* תרומות *Trumos*
and מעשרות *Maasros* without having asked so now they would say oh
you know what we've seen that this is happening sometimes that people
are being מפריש mafrish, *mafrish* even though they really shouldn't be being
מפריש mafrish *mafrish* it's happening everybody stop selling now that we've said
everybody stop selling now everybody is entitled to go ahead and be
מפריש mafrish *mafrish* so it's like two stages first we're concerned about
the phenomenon then we make this rule once we make this rule
then people actually can rely that these are the facts that actually
are are are in place okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this אמר רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana
אמר רבי יוחנן מחלוקת בכדי חסרונן *Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan machlokes b'kdei chesronan* this debate about whether you're allowed to
Sell or not when they're starting to rot is only when they
are rotting at the normal rate. Now, a later משנה mishna. is
going to talk about that, about if you go ahead and you
entrust with me some stuff and I give it back to you,
and it's not all there, but the reason it's not all there
is because, you know, a little bit of it got, you know,
like disintegrated and a little bit like maybe was, you know, eaten
by, spoiled or something, but it was the natural rate of that
stuff happening, then you don't have any claim against me, okay? And
the גמרא Gemara later discusses what is that natural rate, you know,
how much, you know, what's the proportional quantity of stuff over the
course of a year? So what the תירוץ teirutz is, so this
debate here about whether you're allowed to sell it is when stuff
is depreciating at a normal rate, okay? But אבל יותר מכדי חסרונן,
aval yoter michedei chesronan, but if it's more than their normal rate,
okay, so it looks like it's depreciating twice as fast, all right,
in that case, I lost my place, אבל יותר מכדי חסרונן דברי
הכל מוכרין בבית דין aval yoter michedei chesronan divrei hakol mocherin beveit
din and everybody says that if it looks like your stuff is
depreciating twice as fast, everyone says, oh in that case you really
have to protect the owner, forget any of these other concerns, protect
the owner, okay?
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: דברי הכל מוכרין בבית
דין. divrei hakol mocherin beveit din. עד רב נחמן בר יצחק ודאי
פליגא. Ad Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak vadai pliga.
Now this certainly goes against רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak for רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak it wasn't
about protecting the owner, it was about the possibility that you're feeding
somebody תרומה, terumah? you know, this might be תרומה terumah, and somebody
is violating the law of תרומה, terumah. which is a very serious
sin. So even if the owner's loss is enormous, right, nevertheless how
can I possibly give this to somebody else and have them eat
maybe this is תרומה terumah? and have them eat תרומה? terumah. So
it can't be justified based on the rate of loss. Okay, but
עד רב כהנא, ad Rav Kahana, now how about רב כהנא? Rav
Kahana מי לימא דפליגי? Mi leima depligi? Would it argue? Because רב
כהנא Rav Kahana said it was basically about protecting the owner wants
his own property. So maybe disagrees, because maybe רב כהנא Rav Kahana
would say that even with a huge loss, the owner wants his
own property. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, no, then it depends
on how big the loss is. כי קאמר רב כהנא, Ki ka'amar
Rav Kahana, when does רב כהנא say the owner wants to protect
his own property even if it's going to come to a loss?
בכדי חסרונן קאמר, Bechedei chesronan ka'amar, only with the normal rate. If
it's a faster rate of depreciation, he'd rather just protect his investment
and have it sold. And have it sold.
So the גמרא Gemara. says, הרוצה בקב שלו מתשעה קבין של חבירו
קאמר, Harotzeh bekav shelo mitishah kabin shel chaveiro ka'amar, but it says
like you would rather want it one-ninth of the value rather than
something that isn't yours. All right, גוזמא בעלמא, Guzma be'alma, we were
exaggerating. Okay, so basically, for רב כהנא the idea is it's
about what's in the owner's best interest. So at a normal rate
of loss, it's in the owner's best interest to accept the loss
and to keep his own property. At a faster rate of loss,
at least that's what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you always protect the investment.
But at a faster rate of loss, everybody agrees you protect the
owner's investment. It's all about protecting the owner. Whereas if the concern
is protecting the consumer who might buy it and eat תרומה, terumah
for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma at least, that's the תנא קמא's
Tanna Kamma concern, no degree of loss of the owner can justify
exposing people to that risk. All right, so let's take a look
where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you
on this: ומסיקנא דבעל הבית עושה אותן תרומה ומעשר על מקום אחר.
Umasikna de'ba'al habayit oseh osan terumah u'ma'aser al makom acher. We just
have now said that once this law is in place that you're
not allowed to sell, the owner can be confident that the שומר
still has it and can go ahead and be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות,
mafrish terumos u'ma'asros, use it for תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'ma'asros וליחוש דלמא
הוו להו יותר מכדי חסרונן
וזבנינהו וקא אכיל טבלים. V'leichush dilma havu lehu yoter michedei chesronan v'zavnineihu
v'ka achil tevalim. One minute, now that you've said that there are
exceptions to the rule, right, that if it's depreciating too fast it
could be sold, how can the owner feel confident to be מפריש
תרומות ומעשרות? mafrish terumos u'ma'asros? Right? So now the גמרא Gemara is
sort of saying it in the, you could say it in two
ways. Maybe the owner has to feel, maybe the owner, I mean,
actually, I said it the wrong way. The גמרא Gemara asks the
better question. The גמרא Gemara. says, since we've told the owner that
he can feel confident and be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות, mafrish terumos u'ma'asros,
now even if you started with your point about I just want
to protect the owner's investment and give the owner back what he
most wants back, like that's where you started, like does he want
his own property, does he want the value? Okay, that's where you
started. It was all protecting the owner. But now that we've told
the people that they can feel confident and go ahead and be
מפריש תרומות ומעשרות, mafrish terumos u'ma'asros, then even if my responsibility to
the owner should mandate that I should sell it because the rate
is so fast, how could I do it? It might be תרומות
ומעשרות, trumos u'ma'asros and I'm exposing people to eating, you know, תרומה.
terumah. Okay? So it's all very nice that it started by a
responsibility to the owner and weighing what the owner would want to
get back, but now that we've told owners they can be מפריש,
mafrish how could I ever go ahead and sell it, even if,
even if I need to protect the owner's investment?
In case someone buys it and takes תרומה?
Terumah Well, they can't take תרומה. terumah But the question is maybe
I could sell it to כהנים, kohanim, right, which is what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, וליחוש דלמא הוו להו יותר מכדי חסרונן וזבנינהו וקא אכיל טבלים.
V'leichush dilma havu lehu yoter michedei chesronan v'zavnineihu v'ka achil tevalim. The
גמרא Gemara says... ויתיר מכדי חסרונם לא שכיח. V'yasir mich'dei chesronam lo
shachiach. That's very rare. Okay. That so, the... okay. ואי משתכחי v'ee
mishtakchei מה? mah? So the גמרא Gemara says who cares that it's
rare. In the case that it happens מה, mah, what do you
call? זבנינן להו? zavninan lehu? Okay. So what? But once in a
thousand times it'll happen and we're going to allow it to happen.
How do you allow it to happen? In that case it might
be תרומה ומעשרות. terumah u'ma'asros. וליחוש שמא עשאן בעל הבית תרומה ומעשר
על מקום אחר. v'lichush shema asaan ba'al habayis terumah u'ma'aser al makom
acher. Still the same question, so it only happens once in a
thousand times, but how do you allow it in that once in
a thousand times? So it says no. כי מזבנינן נמי לכהנים בדמי
תרומה מזבנינן להו. Ki mizabninan nami l'kohanim bidmei terumah mizabninan lehu. No,
no, no. In that case we would only sell it to
כהנים kohanim because and then because it might be תרומה terumah, and
we would only be able to charge them the value of תרומה.
terumah תרומה terumah goes at a much lower market rate because it
because it has first of all there's a smaller market, it can
only be bought by כהנים. kohanim. Second of all you have to
be טהור. tahor. If you get it טמא tamei you can't eat
it. So תרומה terumah maybe sells at half the price of normal
stuff. So what I would have to do is I would have
to treat it as תרומה, terumah sell it to כהנים, kohanim, tell
them this is probably תרומה terumah and only charge them תרומה terumah,
rates to sell it to them. Which by the way means that
the rate of loss must be really very high because it's more
in the owner's interest to get the תרומה terumah price for this
grain than for me to hold on to it. Okay. But nevertheless
in that scenario where that is true, that's what I would do.
Now that we've told the owners that they can be confident that
we מפריש תרומה, mafrish terumah, my responsibility to the owner to protect
the investment would only would have to take into account the fact
that it might be תרומה terumah, and I would have to treat
this and tell people that I'm treating this as תרומה terumah and
only in that under those context would I be allowed to sell
it. All right. חזק וברוך. Chazak u'varuch. If
it's not תרומה, terumah. then okay the owner lost out his money,
but I did the best I could do.
The כהן kohen can just eat it as if it was.
But the owner, right, eating it as תרומה terumah just means you're
being more careful with it. Okay. What it really is is a
sad story because I could have sold it for more money and
the owner lost out on some of that money, but what could
I do? I have my responsibility to the owner and I'm responsibility
to the larger society and this is the only way I can
balance it.
חזקה doesn't come in at all like I'm משקיע mashkia to this
grain to you, a friend's in Brazil. Right.
Why don't we why don't we just say it's a חזקה that
it has its previous status? Especially especially given the fact that תוספות
points out that as a general rule you're not supposed to be
מפריש mafrish if it's not all together. I know, it is interesting
that the גמרא Gemara didn't say that. Right. But why didn't the
גמרא Gemara just say it's true the owner's allowed to do it
but a חזקה that the owner didn't do it? I don't know,
I don't know why the גמרא didn't say that. Okay. So let's
take a look at what's at the next line of the גמרא.
Okay.
So the גמרא says like this. Now, so the גמרא says like
this. ולאביי נמי, u'l'Abaye nami, now we've said that רב נחמן בר
יצחק נמי, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak nami, now we've said that רב
נחמן Rav Nachman בר יצחק who focused on the whole concern being
about that it might be תרומה, truma. we've claimed why we claimed
this is not clear but we've claimed that according to him
even if regardless of the rate of loss you wouldn't be allowed
to sell it. Well why is that true? Now we have a
way that you could sell it and not have to worry about
the whole תרומה truma. concern, right, if you treat it as תרומה.
truma. So why would רב נחמן Rav Nachman בר יצחק disagree? ורב
נחמן בר יצחק נמי, V'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak nami, he's the one
that said that the reason not to sell it is the תרומה
truma concern. That was the original reason not to sell it. So
ניזבנינהו לכהנים בדמי תרומה. nizabnineihu l'kohanim bidmei terumah. So you have the
same solution and at least in some cases you should be allowed
to sell it. So the גמרא says no. בהא פליגי. B'ha peligi.
This is what the debate boils down to. דרבה בר בר חנה
סבר, D'Rabbah bar bar Chana savar, רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chana? who is the one who says that the issue is
יתיר מכדי חסרונם, yasir mich'dei chesronam,
right, was that that was רבה בר בר חנה? One minute.
Yeah, that says that once it's more it's a high rate of
return you're allowed to sell it, a high rate of loss you're
allowed to sell it. So he says דרבה בר בר חנה סבר,
d'Rabbah bar bar Chana savar, now I lost my place again, here.
יתיר מכדי חסרונם לא שכיח. Yasir mich'dei chesronam lo shachiach. Okay, it's
not very common like we said before, okay, מידי at all. וכי
משתכחי V'chi mishtakchei and in the rare cases that it occurs, לכמה
הוא דהוה. l'kamah hu d'havah. It occurs in the future. I mean
everything occurs in the future but it means it occurs only after
a long time. Things will only begin to depreciate at you know
at a higher than normal rate after a long period of time
when they're rotting. Therefore what, therefore what?
Just to just go with it. לכמה הוא דהוה. L'kamah hu d'havah.
יתיר מכדי חסרונם הוא דהוה יתיר מכדי חסרונם. Yasir mich'dei chesronam hu
d'havah yasir mich'dei chesronam. Only over a long period of time will
it be higher than the normal rate of loss. ואי עביד להו
בעל הבית תרומה ומעשר במקום אחר V'ee avid lehu ba'al habayis terumah
u'ma'aser b'makom acher and if the owner did make it תרומה ומעשר
terumah u'ma'aser מקמי דהוו להו יתיר מכדי חסרונם עביד להו. mikamei d'havu
lehu yasir mich'dei chesronam avid lehu. He would have made it תרומה
ומעשר terumah u'ma'aser before it got to this high rate of loss,
before I sold it. Okay. Therefore when I'm getting ready to sell
it, it's now I've been holding onto it for a year and
a half and now it has this accelerated rate of depreciation. I
can be confident that if the owners were going to, they don't
always take תרומה ומעשר terumah u'ma'aser obviously, but if they were going
to take
תרומה ומעשר. terumah u'ma'aser. When it becomes at higher rate after a
year and a half and I'm ready to sell it, I can
say, if they were to have taken תרומות and מעשרות they would
have done it by now, נזבנינהו לכהנים בדמי תרומה nisbeninu l'kohanim bidmei
truma and I can treat it as תרומה. truma. So that's at
least a solution of solving my responsibilities to the owners and solving
my responsibility to the larger population. Okay, that works, but רב נחמן
בר יצחק is basically saying never sell it because it might be
תרומה. truma, Why not use this solution? So he says, סבר, savar,
יתם מצד חסרונה משכח שכיח, yeisom mitzad chisarona mishcha shchiach, actually that's
a pretty common occurrence. Okay. What? Yeah I know, which is the
whole thing we discussed before, like we don't like it when rabbis
debate the facts, you know, rather than the law. But anyway, דכי
הוי להו לאלתר הוא דהוי להו. d'ki havi lehu l'altar hu d'havei
lehu. And usually you start seeing right away that it's having a
higher rate of depreciation. Maybe they have different ways of measuring rates
of depreciation. ואי אמרת נזבנינהו, ve'im amrat nisbeninu hu, and if you
give somebody a license to sell it, the concern is not that
the other person will be eating תרומה. truma There's a solution to
that, treat it as if it's תרומה truma? and sell it to
the person and sell it to the person and have the person
to a כהן kohein and have them eat it as תרומה. truma
No, the concern is you're going to sell it before the owners
are מפריש, and then the owners are going to be מפריש later
thinking you haven't sold it. Okay. ואי אמרת נזבנינהו, ve'im amrat nisbeninu
hu, זימנין דקדים מזבני להו, zimnin d'kadim mazvin lehu, you'll sell it
right up front, you know, early on, ועביד להו בעל הבית תרומה
ומעשר ממקום אחר, v'avid lehu ba'al habayis truma u'ma'aser mimakom acher, and
then when the owner, you know, you sell it in one month,
you say, "Oh my god, this is depreciating so fast I gotta
sell it." And then two months after that, three months after they
gave it to you, the owner is going to be מפריש תרומות
ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros thinking you're still holding onto it. So לא ידע
דזבנינהו, lo yada d'zvina, they don't know you've sold it, ואכל טבלים.
v'achal tvelin. And then I'm not concerned about the guy you sold
it to, he'll treat it as תרומה, truma. okay, fine, whatever, he's
safe. But the owners I'm concerned about. They think that they were
מפריש תרומה mafrish truma. and it worked, and they didn't because somebody
else owns it now and they're going to eat טבל. tevel. Okay.
So it's all very complicated, but bottom line is, what approach says
my primary concern is the owners and therefore if it's depreciating too
fast I would everybody would agree that I could sell it. What
about the fact that it might be תרומה? truma, Well, to that
I add the fact that I think that this scenario will only
happen after a very long period of time, so if the owner
were going to take תרומה truma he would have taken it by
now, and the person who buys it will treat it as תרומה.
truma The other approach says don't sell it because there's too many
תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-ma'asrot, concerns. What does that mean? It means even
at a very high rate of depreciation don't sell it because even
if the other guy treats it as תרומה, truma. the owner might
think you're still holding onto it and the owner will eat טבל.
tevel. So תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-ma'asrot concerns has to dominate the concern
and therefore that can never be overridden by concerns about the owner's
loss. Okay, you're never allowed to sell it. Okay, so that's two
ways of describing the position of the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Let's
continue in the גמרא.
מיתיבי, Meise, let's say that שומר was acting as a kind
of
he was, but as soon as it leaves his control you can't
be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות trumot u-ma'asrot on grain that somebody else owns.
So that's the problem.
But it's like a retroactive because if it was sold as תרומה
truma. and treated as תרומה truma
yes, but it wasn't yet, meaning meaning meaning
I sold Eli's grain to you. I thought maybe it was תרומה.
truma You are going to bring it to your family of כהנים
Kohanim and they're whatever they're all going to eat it, okay, fine.
And you're so you're going to do the right thing. But מה
mah but the reality was it wasn't taken as תרומה. truma You
guys have eaten it at this stage or it's in your possession.
And now a month later Eli thinks I still am holding onto
it and he's מפריש תרומה. mafrish truma But what is he מפריש
תרומה truma, on? Not the grain in my house, I don't have
grain in my house. The grain in your house, it's already eaten,
even if it's not eaten he doesn't own it anymore. So that's
the problem.
But he's just retroactively given it the status that
No he can't do it retroactively. I see your point. It can't
work retroactively, it only works from the time he does it. Right.
Moving forward. If תרומה worked retroactively that would be a great solution
but it doesn't. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this, מיתיבי,
Meise,
I'll ask you on this. המפקיד פירות אצל חברו והרקיבו, Ha-mapkid peiros
etzel chaveiro v'irkivu, you put you entrusted fruit to your friend and
they rotted. יין והחמיץ, Yayin v'hechmitz, wine began to become vinegary. שמן
והביש, shemen v'heivish, oil which spoiled. דבש והדביש, Devash v'hidvish, honey which
spoiled.
So it's interesting, the word for spoiling honey is the word for
honey itself. So רשי, Rashi, really honey does not spoil, I don't
know what to say, maybe it means it congealed and it got
hard. Put it in a little warm water it'll- I don't know
what to say.
Anyway, I'm going to make a grammatical point, I'm going to make
a grammatical point which רשי Rashi makes, which is that the
word for honey itself- oh, it says date honey. Oh, date honey.
Oh. Date honey. All right. Okay. I was going to make a
grammatical point, I was going to make
a grammatical point which רשי Rashi makes,
which is that the word for honey itself Oh, date honey. Oh,
oh, date honey. Oh, I see. Material. Alright. Okay, I was going
to make a grammatical point, I was going to make a grammatical
point which רש"י Rashi makes, which is that the word for root
itself can mean to un-honey it. So רש"י Rashi says, alright, right,
so רש"י Rashi says לשרש lesharesh or להשריש. lehashrish.
להשריש lehashrish means to put roots, לשרש lesharesh means to uproot, right?
So you actually have that in English too, like you can get
nuts that are shelled and salted. So shelled means the shells are
removed, salted means the salt is added.
So anyway, okay, save your wife honey because you don't know what
you mean.
Alright. That's very nice.
Bee honey
is not subject to תרומה and מעשר.
maiser. Oh, that's true. Bee honey is not subject to תרומה and
מעשר. maiser. That's a good point. Oh, okay. הרי זה לא יגע
בהן.
Okay.
Anyway, all this stuff is happening, don't touch it. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. That presumably
is the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of our משנה. mishna, I don't
care what's happening to it, leave it alone. Okay. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim
omrim,
but the sages say, which presumably is the רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel of our משנה, mishna, עושה להם תקנה. oseh
lahem takkana. No, you you you take care of the situation. מוכרן
בבית דין, Mokhran b'veit din, do it in the presence of a
בית דין beit din so it's all above board. מוכרן לאחרים ולא
מוכרן לעצמו, Mokhran l'acherim v'lo mokhran l'atzmo,
sell it to other people not to yourself. So A, בית דין
ensures you're getting a fair price and you're not cheating the owner
that way, and B, maybe you're just doing it for, forget the
price, maybe you're just interested in it for yourself, right? Even if
you are going to pay the full price. So sell it to
other people, don't sell it to yourself. Everything, you have to keep
your hands clean of the whole thing and do it to protect
the owner's interest.
Okay. כיוצא בו, Kayotzei bo, similar when you have to do something
to protect the person but also make sure that you're above suspicion.
גבאי צדקה בזמן שאין להם עניים לחלק, Gabai tzedaka bizman she'ein lahem
aniyim l'chalek, if they don't have money to give out the money
and they're dealing with copper coins, and copper because they give out
small bills to the עניים, aniyim, copper coins, but copper coins you
know rust. So what do they do? פורטין לאחרים, Portin l'acherim, they
swap them with other people, like the copper for silver, ואין פורטין
לעצמן, v'ein portin l'atzman, but not for themselves so nobody should be
suspect that maybe they you know didn't you know gave themselves a
too generous rate of return or something. Copper doesn't rust. Copper doesn't
rust. It gets, what does it get, it gets moldy or something,
doesn't it? It oxidizes. It becomes green. It becomes green. That's what
I meant. That's not called rust, what is that called, oxidizing? Fine.
But I meant green, I've definitely seen those like really green when
they find them in those archaeological digs they're like all green and
disgusting.
Okay. גבאי תמחוי, Gabai tamchui, now the overseers of the soup kitchen
where they go and they collect food from all the homeowners and
they distribute it to the poor. בזמן שאין להם עניים לחלק, Bizman
she'ein lahem aniyim l'chalek, if there's not enough poor to give it
out to, what do you do with the food, right? You can't
store it for a long period of time. מוכרן לאחרים, Mokhran l'acherim,
sell it to others, ואין מוכרן לעצמן, v'ein mokhran l'atzman, not for
themselves. Anyway, and that's the הלכה. Very interesting about how to, you
know, yeah exactly, about you know your responsibility to others and make
sure nobody suspects you in the transaction and so on.
Now those foods don't require תרומה, in other words, יין, yayin, all
those are foods that you don't...
No, they do! But that's the point, that's the debate of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. Okay, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is presumably רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, don't touch it, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
says sell it. But the question is if that matches up the
opinions on the משנה, Mishnah. but here clearly it's faster rate of
depreciation if the stuff is spoiled, right? Or spoiling. So how... and
it seems that you still don't sell it. So let's take a
look. קתני מיהת, Katani mi'at, we taught nevertheless, פירות והרקיבו, peirot v'hirkiu,
what? לאו אפילו יתר מכדי חסרונם, Lav afilu yeter mikdei chisronam,
it sounds like even faster than the rate of depreciation you still
can't sell it? לא בכדי חסרונם. Lo, bikdei chisronam. No, no, we
only mean the normal rate of depreciation. The word says that can't
be! והיין והחמיץ, V'hayayin v'heechmitz, שמן והבאיש. shemen v'hivish.
We're talking about becoming vinegar, right? And being spoiled. יתר מכדי חסרונם?
Yeter mikdei chisronam? שמן והבאיש דבש והבאיש יתר מכדי חסרונם? Shemen v'hivish,
dvash v'hivish, yeter mikdei chisronam? That's
clearly much greater than the normal rate of depreciation and it still
says don't touch it. It says no, שאני הני כיון דקם קם.
shani hani kivan d'kam kam. Yeah, there the problem is it's too
late. It's already became vinegar, it already became spoiled. So you're right,
so the reason there רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if it was
spoiling רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree to sell it, but once
it's already
spoiled רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says alright so now don't sell it.
What are you going to do? Of course then the question is
so then why do the חכמים chachamim say sell it, right? What's
left to happen now? So let's take a look. שמן והבאיש דבש
והבאיש למי חזי? Shemen v'hivish, dvash v'hivish, l'mai chazei? So first the
גמרא says one minute,
if it's already spoiled who's buying it? What good are you going
to use with spoiled oil, spoiled honey? So the גמרא says שמן
חזי לגלדאי. shemen chazi l'girdai. No,
oil can be used
for leather. ודבש לכתיתת גמלי. V'dvash l'chtishat gamli.
And honey that's spoiled can still be used for rubbing into like
sores on a camel. Okay, so that's why it's got a market
but it's already spoiled. So it's too late, so that's why רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says don't sell it. So why are the חכמים
chachamim selling it? וחכמים אומרים עושה להם תקנה מוכרן בבית דין. V'chachamim
omrim oseh lahem takkana mokhran b'veit din. מאי תקנה עביד? Mai takkana
avid?
How are you helping the owners? It's already spoiled. So אמר רב
אשי
לקנקנים. Amar Rav Ashi l'kankanim. Oh no, what you're doing is you're
protecting the jars. You got spoiled wine in a jar, okay, if
you don't do anything the jar The jar's gonna get ruined. The
גמרא *Gemara* says that's like that old story about the guy that's
trying, there's a place where they got the guards set up and
he brings bicycles back and forth and they check it and there's
nothing in it. Turns out he's smuggling bicycles the whole time.
Here you're selling it to protect the jars. במאי קמיפלגי *be-mai kamiflagi*?
What's the debate about? Why isn't רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* saying sell
it to protect the jars? מר סבר להפסד מרובה חששו להפסד מועט
לא חששו *Mar savar le-hefsed merubeh hashoshu le-hefsed muat lo hashoshu*. The
same רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says don't sell it, the way we're
framing it, unless it's a high rate of loss. He also says
don't sell it if all you're doing is just protecting a jar.
That's not enough of a loss to entitle you to sell the
owner's property. וחכמים סברי ואפילו להפסד מועט נמי חששו *Va-Chachamim savri ve-afillu
le-hefsed muat nami hashoshu*. No, any type of protection of property. The
same way they debate will you sell it at a normal rate
of loss to protect the owner's property or only at a high
rate of loss? That's how we framed it. The debate is when
it's depreciating at a normal rate, do you sell it or not?
But if it's a high rate of loss, everybody agrees you sell
it. In parallel, they debate
if it's already spoiled and all that's left is the two-dollar jar,
is that enough of a reason to sell it? That's the debate
that they're having here.
Unless you think there's some markets for the spoiled stuff because otherwise
you could just pour it out.
That's a good point too. That's actually a good question. Then why
doesn't everybody agree that you sell the contents and keep the jar?
I don't know the answer to that. Let's move on. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* אומר ימכרו
בבית דין משום כהשבת אבידה *omer yimkeru
be-veis din mishum ke-hashevat aveidah*.
Do you think they buy the jar when they buy the contents?
Why don't you make a special arrangement? I don't know. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* אומר ימכרו
בבית דין משום כהשבת אבידה לבעלים *omer yimkeru be-veis din mishum ke-hashevat
aveidah la-bealim*. No, he says even at a normal rate of loss,
sell it, the way we're framing this debate, sell it because you're
protecting the owner's investment. איתמר itmar, *Itmar*, רבי אבא בריה דרבי יעקב
*Rabbi Abba brei de-Rabbi Yaakov* אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל *amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. We rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. ורבא *Ve-Rava* אמר רב
נחמן הלכה כדברי חכמים *amar Rav Nachman halacha ke-divrei Chachamim*. We rule
like the חכמים *Chachamim*, don't sell it at a normal rate of
loss. ואמר רבי יוחנן חדא זימנא *Ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan hada zimna*. Didn't
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* already implicitly tell us we rule like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*? דאמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן כל מקום ששנה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל במשנתנו הלכה
כמותו *De-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan kol makom she-shanah
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel be-mishnateinu halacha kemoto*. Whenever רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
*Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* appears in a משנה *Mishnah*, we rule like
him. Whenever his opinion appears in a משנה *Mishnah*, we rule like
it with three exceptions: חוץ מערב וצידן וראיה אחרונה *chutz me-arev ve-Tzidan
ve-raayah acharonah*. A משנה *Mishnah* that deals with a cosigner, a guarantor
I should say, וצידן *ve-Tzidan*, a whole thing
about witnesses
that are in צידן *Tzidan*, the name of a place, וראיה אחרונה
*ve-raayah acharonah*, and there are two debates about bringing proofs to בית
דין *Beis Din* and in the second debate about bringing proofs. We
don't have to worry what those are, but other than those three
exceptions, we always rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel*. Why do we need to say here specifically that we rule
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* according to רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*? The גמרא *Gemara* says אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן
*Amorai ninhu ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yochanan*. Yes, there's a debate of אמוראים *Amoraim*.
One אמורא *Amora* thinks that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* made a global
statement, we always rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel*, and therefore he wouldn't have had to say it in this
case. And the other אמורא *Amora* says no, he didn't make that
global statement, but in this case, he did rule like רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*. Either way, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
is saying we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel* that you sell it even without a high rate of loss.
Now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: מרבן שמעון בן גמליאל נשמע
דמורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי *Mi-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel nishma de-moridin karov le-nichsei
shavuy*. From רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*'s position that
you're very responsive to the loss of the owner and even to
take liberties with the owner's property because you understand that's the tradeoff.
We're trying to protect the owner's investment, how much license does that
give us to take liberties with the owner's property? From רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* that says you always tip in
favor of protecting the investment, we could infer that you will allow
a relative to go down into the property of somebody who has
been taken captive. What does this mean? Somebody is taken captive
by the army or the enemy and there's obviously a concern that
he might
die. Now his fields are laying fallow. What do you do? You
just let his fields lay fallow in the time? The question is
why don't we do the following: let's take his most closest relative,
his son, the guy who will inherit him. That person has a
clear invested interest in protecting the property because even if it's so
and have him work the fields. If it turns out that the
father is dead, so it's his field, he keeps it. If it
turns out that the father is alive, so he's protected the investment
of the father. Are you allowed to do that or do you
have to say
no, we don't have a right to go ahead and to access
take liberties with the owner's property just because we're trying to protect
the owner's investment? That's a very parallel debate to our debate of
selling the fruit. How much liberty do we give us to protect
the owner's investment? Let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
*Amar Rav Yehuda*, it says like this: מרבן שמעון בן גמליאל
נשמע *Mi-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel nishma*, from רבן שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel* who says we have to focus on protecting the
value, we can infer דמורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי *de-moridin karov le-nichsei shavuy*.
You can have the relative go down and work the fields of
the person taken captive. מדברי רבנן *Midivrei Rabbanan*... מדרבנן נשמע דאין מורידין
קרוב לנכסי שבוי. The Rabbis who say you have to tip in
favor of not taking liberties, we should say that you don't work
the fields of the captive. ממאי? mimmai? Now the גמרא says one
minute, who says that there's the same debate? דילמא עד כאן לא
קאמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל הכא אלא משום דקא כליא קרנא? dilma
ad kan lo ka'amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hacha ella mishum deka
kalya karna? Maybe רבן שמעון בן גמליאל here only gives you liberties
because the actual principal is being lost, right? No, the fruit, the
fruit is rotting, but by the field you're losing profit but you're
not losing the principal, the field is still there. אבל התם הכא
נמי דאין מורידין. aval hatam hacha nami de-ein moridin. There, where it's
not about the principal, it's just profit, he would say duh, you
know, keep your hands
off. ועד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן הכא אלא איכא דרב כהנא ואיכא
דרב נחמן בר יצחק. ve-ad kan lo ka'amrei Rabbanan hacha ella ika
de-Rav Kahana ve-ika de-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. There's particular reasons because we're
afraid it might be תרומות ומעשרות, we think that somebody wants their
own fruit rather than
someone else's. אבל התם הכא נמי דמורידין. aval hatam hacha nami demoridin.
Those reasons aren't relevant. There's not—not afraid he's taking תרומות ומעשרות on
the ground, okay? Right, and it's not his fruit yet that he
wants more than somebody else's fruit. It's just about making profit off
of this land that is now laying fallow. So there's reasons to
say one thing in one case and one in the other. They're
similar, but you might not come out the same way in both
decisions. So the גמרא says למימרא דתרתי טעמי נינהו? lemeimra de-tartei ta'amei
ninhu? You think that there are different reasons that can govern those
two cases? והאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל.
ve-ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So one
minute, רב יהודה says in the name of שמואל Shmuel that we
rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל in our משנה. ואמר שמואל מורידין
קרוב לנכסי שבוי. ve-amar Shmuel moridin karov lenichsei shavui. And the same
שמואל Shmuel says that you have them go and work the fields.
So presumably it's the same פסק. psak. רבינא משום דחד טעמא הוא?
Ravina mishum de-chad ta'ama hu? Isn't it because it's really the same
פסק? psak? So it's a funny argument. The גמרא says לא תרי
טעמי נינהו. lo terei ta'amei ninhu. No, there are different considerations. It's
true שמואל Shmuel in both cases rules in favor of protecting the
owner's financial interests and taking liberties with the owner's property, but that
doesn't mean that they go hand in hand. There are different—there's a
different calculus. And it just so happens that שמואל Shmuel in both
cases tips in favor of protecting the owner's, you know, investment. הכא
נמי מסתברא. hacha nami mistabra. You know what? It makes sense that
there's different factors. דאמר רבא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כחכמים. de-amar Rava
amar Rav Nachman halacha ke-Chachamim. Because רבא Rava says in the name
of רב נחמן הלכה כחכמים halacha ke-Chachamim which says you don't touch
the fruit. Okay? ואמר רב נחמן מורידין קרוב לנכסי שבוי. ve-amar Rav
Nachman moridin karov lenichsei shavui. And רב נחמן himself says but you
do work the fields. So you see in one case we could
say don't touch because of this reason of I don't know, you
want your own fruit or תרומות ומעשרות or whatever, and in the
other case we could say work the field so he doesn't go
to loss.
One's מטלטלין metaltelin and one's קרקע. karka.
Right, and all those reasons. אלא שמע מינה תרי טעמי נינהו. ella
shema mina terei ta'amei ninhu. You see that there are different factors
and you come out one way in one case and one way
in the other case. שמע מינה. shema mina. That's a good point.
איתמר, was taught: שבוי שנשבה. shavui she-nishba.
Now here is the actual debate that we referred to. Somebody that
was taken captive. רב אמר אין מורידין קרוב לנכסיו. Rav amar ein
moridin karov lenichsav. You don't have the immediate relative work the fields.
שמואל אמר מורידין קרוב לנכסיו. Shmuel amar moridin karov lenichsav. You have
him work the fields because, you know, he stands to inherit it
anyway. He's going to take protection over it. Okay? And worst case
is that his father comes back, he gives it to his father,
it's still, you know, his father's property he'd still eventually get, or
who knows. Anyway, בששמעו בו שמת. be-she-shamu bo she-met. If you heard
the guy is dead. כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמורידין. kulei alma lo
pligi demoridin. Everybody agrees that the son now works the field. Now
you could say duh, it's the son's property, but that's a technical
term duh. Anyway, but so the point is you don't know he's
dead. There's not testimony that he's dead. You've heard he's dead. Reports
are coming back that he's dead. So it might be that he's
not dead. But nevertheless, once those are the reports, then this guy,
you can have him work it, he thinks he's the owner anyway,
he thinks the father is dead, okay, he can—then everybody agrees: have
him work the field. He might be dead and he's going to
take care of it anyway, so have him work the field. Everybody
agrees. כי פליגי בשלא שמעו בו שמת. ki pligi be-she-lo shamu bo
she-met.
The debate is you know he's captive and he might be dead
but he might not. רב אמר אין מורידין. Rav amar ein moridin.
You don't. דילמא מפסיד להו. dilma mafsid lehu. Because maybe he will,
you know, he will hurt the field. Maybe רש״י Rashi even says,
maybe what he's going to try to do is he's going to
try to strip-mine. He's not going to take like the care as
a long-term owner. He'll try to get some immediate profit out of
the field, right, and before his father comes back or something. Okay?
So it's actually might be more damaging to the owner to allow
the guy to work it. ושמואל אמר מורידין. ve-Shmuel amar moridin. No,
כיון דאמר מר שיימינן להו כאריס. kivan de-amar mar shaiminan lehu ke-aris.
Since we're going to say—we haven't said yet—that even if the father...
I'm saying father, really could be any, you know, whoever the relative
is. But if—since even if the father comes back, the guy who
works it gets a portion of what he got—what he did. Okay?
He'll get his—like a normal אריס—he'll aris get a third of the
crops. So in that case לא מפסיד להו. lo mafsid lehu. He's
going to be a responsible—because the
father might not come back for ten years. He's going to want
to keep on—you know, he's not going to say I better grab
it all now. In either case he's—has a vested interest in maintaining
the profitability, the long-term profitability. bility of the field. Okay, so I
guess we will stop there. We got very close to catching up;
we're going to try to keep a similar pace tomorrow and be
fully caught up.
Rabbi, in the previous early case about